<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Full and true relation of all the proceedings at the assizes holden at Maidstone, for the countie of Kent</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2316A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10329911</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10329911</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44880</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1384:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Full and true relation of all the proceedings at the assizes holden at Maidstone, for the countie of Kent</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44880:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <head>The full and True RELATION OF ALL THE PROCEEDINGS AT THE ASSIZES Holden at MAIDSTONE, FOR THE Countie of Kent.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Which began on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 23d of this inſtant <hi>March,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on <hi>Fryday</hi> the 26th of the ſame. With an exact Account of the moſt remarkable Trials of ſeveral notorious Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, both for Murders and Robberies.</p>
               <p>And more eſpecially of one <hi>James Wattle</hi> for murthering his Apprentice, and one <hi>Bridges</hi> for hanging a Child up in a Sack and ſmothering it to death in a Chimney, and ſeveral other conſiderable Trials<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> With the number of thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to dye, burn'd in the hand and to be whipt. <date>
                     <add>Printed .2. Aprill. 1680.</add>
                  </date>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>JUſtice in its Annual progreſs ſeldom miſſes to revenge Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts impoſed upon its integrity, and loudmouth d crimes ſtill hurry a deſerved puniſhment on ſuch offending Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants as dare by vile offences to tranſgreſs the beſt of Laws, as may in the ſequel of this dread reſult be ſhowen.</p>
            <p>The firſt that was called to the Bar was <hi>James Wattle,</hi> of the Town of <hi>Maidſtone</hi> Grocer, who was Arraigned and tryed, for Murdering his Apprentice, a Youth of about eighteen years of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44880:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
Age: the manner thus. The deceaſed being his Couſen, or ſome near akin to him, was by his indulgent Parents committed to his Care and tuition, not doubting ſuch barbarous uſuage as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a Friend, and by reaſon of their diſtant living, could no<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſily be informed, but as it is commonly ſeen, a ſtranger is more kind than a perfidious friend, ſo in this; for the youth had <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lived long with him, before he began to uſe him at a groſe R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, that made him complain he was weary of his Life, and all the neighbours took no little notice of the ſame; but as to tho Mu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther for which the Priſoner was tried, be coming home late, th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 6th of <hi>February</hi> laſt, knocked at the Dore, but the Youth as it is ſuppoſed being drowſie by reaſon of his tedious watching, did not quickly hear to let him in, the which ſo inraged his fury that no ſooner was he admitted, but with his unlawful Cudgel, he having ſhut the dore fell upon him ſo unmercifully, that he cried out murther and beg'd of him for Heavens ſake to forbear, but this not at all apeaſed his violence, but continued beating of him till he was tired out of breath, giving him ſo many mortal blowes as cannot well be numbred, and ſo left him weltring in his Gore, who was afterwards by ſome kind hand conveyed to Bed; but in ſome few days after died, complaining of his Maſters cruelty. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death the aforeſaid <hi>Wattle</hi> was apprehended, and bound to anſwer at this Aſſizes, where he pleaded that it was not in the leaſt his deſign to murther him, but to correct him for his negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and that he was ſorry for thoſe unfortunate blowes that had brought the youth to his end, yet upon all circumſtances, the Jury brought it in Manſlaughter and he was burn'd in the hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Field</hi> had two Indictments brought againſt him, for ſtealing a Horſe and a Mare, out of a Farmers grounds near <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> he being taken on the back of one of them, his plea was that he bought them, but could not produce the man be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that ſold them, not bring any proof that he had bought the ſame and having been formerly a man of ill repute, and one that had ſold many horſes to ſeveral in that place, but could give no account how he came by them, the witneſs againſt him being plain and poſitive, the Jury brought him in Guilty, and he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, received Sentance of Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Barker</hi> and <hi>William Beſton</hi> were indicted the former for ſtealing of Sheep, the latter for ſtealing pewter and Linnen to a conſiderable vallue, all which being proved againſt them, they were brought in Guilty, and were both burn'd in the hand.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44880:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
The next was one <hi>Bridges</hi> who was tried <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Mu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thering (after an inhum<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne manner, ſeldome heard of) a little Girl about three years old, the circumſtances as followeth. This murther was committed about eighteen years ſince, yet to ſee how Divine Vengeance finds thoſe out that dye their cruel hands in Blood of innocents, the Girl aforeſaid being as we are credibly informed his Brothers Daughter, was by her Parents deceaſing left with a conſiderable Competency of Monies, if not lands or houſes, left and bequeathed to him, with all the endarments of her departing Friends to be brought up by him the which he moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly undertook but had not long e're the Devil, that grand promoter of all dire Deſigns, prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him on to make her away, and get the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what ſhe had to his own proper intereſt his helliſh ſuggeſtion prevailed ſo far with him that he thought ſit to put it in practiſe, and ſo cunning in contriving, as the better to evade if a diſcovery ſhould be made of Violence done to the Child, that might appear upon ſearch, he tied her up in a thin Sack and hanging it up in the Chimney made a fire with wet ſtraw and other combuſtible matter, which made a noiſome ſmoke and ſo ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered her not at all regarding the diſtreſſed infants crying and intreating her to take her down till she were dead, and finding none obſerved it but thoſe that himſelf thought ſit to make privy to, it <hi>viz.</hi> one <hi>Dux</hi> a ſervant Maid, he cauſed to be buried, and gave out that he had ſent the Child to <hi>London</hi> to be educated there, and ſo ſtopped the mouthes of thoſe that were inquiſitive in that particular but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44880:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
about eighteen years being expired, his Maid fell ſick and thinking death was near at hand, her Guilty Conſcience ſtarted up this moſt inhumane and barbarous Crime, ſo that it long lying heavy on her she at laſt divulged it in its horrid circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as before recited, but recovering of that ſickneſs, her Maſter was apprehended upon thoſe words, she had confeſſed, and being committed, received now his Trial, his plea was that she was light-headed when she ſpoke thoſe words, but he not being able to make out what became of the Child, and there being no other Witneſs but her Confeſſion, the leaſt the Jury could make of this barbarous Act was Man-ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Morgan</hi> was Indicted for Fellony and Burglary for breaking open the houſe of one Mr. <hi>Wincomb</hi> a Victualer, and taking away divers Pots, and Flagons, two Pewter Baſons, and ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Linnen, with 20 <hi>s.</hi> in money, all which amounted to 8 or 9 pounds but being taken with the Goods, he was Committed, yet they could not prove the dore to de broake open, ſo that only the Felony was materially proved, for which he was convicted and burnt in the hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Willis and Thomas Ward, for stealing ſeveral pieces of Linnen from off the Hedges near</hi> Maidſtone, <hi>were found Guilty to the vallue of ten pence, and ordered to be ſcurged for remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There were in all five burn'd in the hand, one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to dye, and two to be whipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44880:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
